ajsm 12/07/2007
suppose source code is now compliant with XVT 5.8 and Visual Studio 8.0.
resolved a display issue associated with the VolEqNum keyword and its description, which were previously being cut off in the list box. 
resolved a display bug so that the new control panel (released with v2.01) is now properly displayed at lower screen resolutions (screen heights < 1024). For these low resolution settings, suppose now runs at variable sizes so that the window is almost maximized within the vertical and horizontal display space (but it is still resizable). 
corrected a typo in the thinning window where height was specified in "inches" instead of "feet".
various changes to accommodate the use of FSVEG's Potential Vegetation (PV) reference code. These are primarily associated with the read/write/edit options for SLF files and how key files are written. Also, the description for field 7 of the STDINFO keyword was changed from "Stand latitude in degrees" to the "Potential vegetation reference code".
support for the ECON extension was added via:
 - a econ keyword file (econ.kwd)
 - an addition to the database extension (EconRpts) to generate output in database table form
 - various event monitor variables were added to support the extension
new fields were added to the DATASCRN and TREEDATA keywords so that users may now specify a species or species group to (in addition to a diameter range) to screened.  
suppose has been updated to support the new naming convention for the FVS base executables (e.g., "FVSxx.exe"). Given that these new executables now contain the Fire & Fuels, Database, and Economic extensions, obsolete executables (e.g., FVSbm replaced bm, bmfm, & bddbfm) have now been deprecated.

nlc 06/08/2007
added CycleAt keyword

cek 05/08/07
updated species codes.

sar 05/01/07
removed the diameter and height distribution post processor
removed the fuels and potential fire table post processor
removed the spectrum export files post processor
edited the svs movies post processor so that the files have *.bmp extensions
edited the default file reference number on the snagout keyword
corrected the treelist keyword since field 7 was being printed to field 6 (which isn't used)
modifed files - ppif.prm, fire.kwd, basekeys.kwd

sar 03/30/2007
added the new em functions potsrate and potreint to function.evm

sar 03/22/07
added the new em function potftype to function.evm

esm 03/09/06
corrected the CRUZFILE keyword, removed the fields in Suppose that weren't
applicable to the keyword.(basekeys.kwd)
added field 2 and field 3 to the CALBSTAT keyword (basekeys.kwd)

esm 02/01/07
added the STANDCN keyword. (basekeys.kwd and keylist.prm)

sar 01/08/07
added the new FuelFoto keyword (fire.kwd and keylist.prm)
added some new warnings to the ones searched for by the error log pp (commands.prm)

esm 01/04/07
added an additional comment to FixCW, FixDG, FixHT (basekeys.kwd)

sar 12/26/06
fixed typos on FFE keywords (fire.kwd)

lrd 11/30/06
added Blister Rust model keywords making them available to crx, nix and sox
executables.
modified files of the Suppose file set:
mkprm
mkprm.bat
program.prm
programsWindosOnly.prm
keylist.prm
brust.kwd - new file of Blist Rust keyword screens

sar 11/1/06
modified the verbage on the snags and salvvol em functions
modified the verbage on the potfseas keyword (fire.kwd) and within fueltrt.prm
changed the default root decay rate for the carbon reports (carbcalc keyword)

cek 10/11/06
updated sliderbox default values on SpecPref and TCondMlt keywords (basekeys.kwd)

cek 10/10/06
updated hackberry species code in Northeast variant (species.prm)
updated management.thin management action, needs Suppose 1.19s (manage.prm)

cek 09/28/06
replaced SeedTree and Shelterwood mgmt actions, needs Suppose 1.19r (manage.prm)

cek 09/22/06
fixed ranges in sliderbox in basekeys.kwd, estab.kwd, fire.kwd, and function.evm.
updated potential fire defaults for sn variant (fire.kwd)
updated description of thin with pileburn (fueltrt.prm)
updated names of fuel treatments (mgmtcats.prm)
added MechThin management action (mgmtcats.prm and inttrtmt.prm)
added FVSStand model output (mdoutputs.prm)

cek 09/20/06
fixed spacing problem in intermediate treatments (inttrtmt.prm)

cek 09/7/06
updated minimum dbh default on scroll bar in clearcut MA (manage.prm)

cek 08/31/06
added svs and compute options to select model outputs (mdoutputs.prm)
updated base model reports to include the EchoSum option (mdoutputs.prm)
updated defaults in regeneration and thinning management actions (manage.prm)
updated and added management categories (mgmtcats.prm)
Added new file called inttrtmt.prm (Intermediate Treatments).
Added it to list in the mkprm.bat and mkprm.
added crown thining, thin individually 'marked' trees, clean or release
cutting, clean or release girdling/chemical treatment, species to target,
and General species group management actions (inttrtmt.prm)
updated defaults on fixmort keyword (basekeys.kwd)

sar 08/25/06
Edited the yardloss options
edited the ffe mgmt actions thin, thin with pb, and mastication
added a new condition (periodicoffset)
changed the carbcalc keyword
added mortality to pileburn and thin with pileburn
added species to the salvage window
added a new thindbh option under fuel treatments

sar 08/15/2006
deleted the old FFE reports management action (mgmtcats.prm and fueltrt.prm)
deleted an erroneous header on the strclass keyword (basekeys.kwd)
updated the select model outputs options (mdoutputs.prm)
add three new FFE management actions (mgmtcats.prm and fueltrt.prm)
added the new strstat event monitor function (function.evm)
added salvage and yardloss management actions
deleted out unused management action entries
added conditions to the conditions library (cond.rul)
added the carbon keywords (fire.kwd, dbs.kwd, and keylist.prm)
adjusted DeFulMod keyword so the new fuel models could be modified.(fire.kwd)

sar 07/10/2006
Added two fields to the FuelInit keyword.

esm 07/07/06
Added new file called mdoutputs.prm. Added it to list in the mkprm.bat and mkprm.

esm 06/28/06
Changed field 1 of the SetPthin from a default of 0, to an empty (null) box.
Modified basekeys.kwd.

esm 06/26/06
added two new event monitor variables, BDBHwtBA and ADBHwtBA, before and after
thin average DBH weighted by stand basal area. Modified variable.evm.

sar 06/16/2006
added a new ffe keyword - CanFProf.  Modifed keylist.prm and fire.kwd.

esm 06/14/06
added 3rd field to the DEFECT keyword, allowing users to ignore volume defect
specified on the input tree record. Modified basekeys.kwd

sar 05/04/06
added the northeast fire model to programs.prm and programsWindosOnly.prm
added the new soilheat keyword to fire.kwd and keylist.prm

esm 3/30/06
Corrected the Dwarf Mistletoe species list for the California varaints. SP was
listed as Shortleaf pine, corrected it to be Sugar pine. Modified mist.kwd.

sar 3/20/06
Modified fueltrt.prm and mgmtcats.prm to improve some of the FFE management actions.
These files are named with a _119 because they should only be compiled when the
new Suppose 1.19 is released.

esm 2/24/06
Modified basekeys.kwd (added a fourth options to the DELOTAB keyword, added the
ECHO and NOECHO keywords). Modified keylist.prm (added the ECHO and NOECHO keywords).

sar 1/18/06
modified basekeys.kwd (edited yardloss verbage for the eastern variants)
modified fire.kwd (edited the snagfall keyword for the region 6 variants)
modified keylist.prm (edited snagfall keyword description)

esm 12/12/05
Added 3 new fields to the TCONDMLT keyword, added 3 new keywords POINTREF,
SETPTTHIN and THINPT, added a field 9 to the SPMCDBH Function. Modified
Basekeys.kwd, keylist.prm, function.evm.

sar 11/15/05
Modified the PotFWind and PotFTemp keywords in fire.kwd to have different
defaults when using the LS variant.

esm 10/27/2005
Modified format of DATASCRN keyword and fixed a problem with the SVS keyword.

esm 10/17/05
Added DATASCRN keyword (modified basekeys.kwd and keylist.prm)

ajm 10/14/05
wwpb.kwd: Added keyword BMOUT.  Amended 3 obsolete output-generating
keywords (I did not remove them, hence old keyword files will still be
readable by Suppose; they are removed from keylist.prm, so they're no longer
available).  Added 4 new *STAND LEVEL* WWPBM keywords.  Made keyword
Disperse a ppe:{bottom} component (it was :{top}).
dbs.kwd: added 4 new WWPBM-DBS table-populating keywords.
entensions.prm: added new category: wwpb2 to extensions, for stand level
WWPBM keywords.  Add BMIN as prefix for wwpb2 to prefixes section.
programsWindosOnly.prm: Added dbs and wwpbm2 to all extensions containing wwpb.
keylist.prm: Added new keywords to WWPBM and DBS sections; commented-out 3
obsolete WWPBM keywords.

sar 09/28/05
Added some new FFE-related management actions.

cek 09/26/05
Edited species.prm so that common names matched variant overviews and FVS
blkdat.f routines.  Edited variant.prm to rename Northeast TWIGS variant to
Northeastern.

esm 09/13/05
Edited the SPGROUP keyword, removed field 2 and changed it so that the maximum
number of species that can be added to the group is not more than the number of
species in the variant. Modified the DEFECT keyword so that users could use the
PARMS button (which would allow them to specify DEFECT by SPGROUP).


sar 08/26/05
Added plant community codes for the LS variant, which will be used in LS-FFE.
Modified mkprm, mkprm.bat, basekeys.kwd, and created habpa_ls.prm.  Also added
some new FFE keywords (POTFPAB, POTFSEAS) and edited SIMFIRE.  Modified fire.kwd
and keylist.prm.  Also edited program.prm and programsWindosOnly.prm so that LS
users could pick the FFE keywords.

esm 08/24/05
Added the SpGroup keyword, modified basekeys.kwd and keylist.prm
Added BRDEN and ARDEN, (Before and After thin Relative Density), to list
of EM variables, also edited the Condition Library to base the Relative Density
Condition on BRDEN, modified variable.evm and cond.rul.

sar 08/24/2005
Added the new DBS STRCLASS keyword into dbs.kwd and keylist.prm.

sar 08/16/05
Altered fire.kwd to update four FFE keywords to implement the new fuel
models - MOISTURE, POTFMOIS, FUELMODL, and DEFULMOD.

esm 08/04/05
Added option 3 (mortality multiplier) to field 6 of the FIXMORT keyword

esm 07/01/05
Added 4th option to field 8 of the SPMCDBH finction (modified function.evm).
Added additional ppe with other extensions packages (modified program.prm
and programsWindosOnly.prm).Corrected descrition of STDIDENT keyword to
allow a 26 characters name,instead of a 8 character name (modified basekeys.kwd)

esm 06/21/05
Added 4 Event Monitor varaibles that were missing, LAT, LONG, STATE,
COUNTY, (modified variable.evm). Chad changed the NE variant common
species names to be consistant with the variant overview for NE,
(species.prm was modified).

esm 06/14/05
Added the THINRDEN keyword, modified basekeys.kwd and keylist.prm.
Added the new species for SORNEC, modified species.prm.

esm 05/11/05
Edited basekeys.kwd to add a 6th field to the SVS keyword which enables
user to ask for metric or imperial units. Also edited ppif.prm so that users
could select either SVS (imperial) or SVS (metric), the additional PP was
created because a different command line was needed to better draw the images
in metric. Also corrected the spelling of "statistics" in the name of the
Calinration Statistics post processor.

esm 04/20/05
Made a correction to species.prm. Parenthesis() instead of brackets {}
were used for Shortleaf pine and Table Mountain pine in the NE species.

esm 03/31/05
Added the TREESZCP keyword, modified basekeys.kwd and keylist.prm
Removed the California Spotted Owl WHR post processor in ppif.prm.

esm 03/15/05
Added the CRUZFILE keyword, modified basekeys.kwd and keylist.prm.
Removed field 6 of the TREELIST keyword, it is no longer used, modified
basekeys.kwd.

sar 03/10/05
Added another new field to the SimFire keyword in fire.kwd.

sar 02/23/05
Added a new field to the SimFire keyword in fire.kwd.

sar 01/05/04
Altered the snags event monitor function.

cek 12/20/04
Updated forest location codes. Modified forest.prm.

sar 12/17/04
Added new Database keywords (FuelRept, MortRept, BurnRept, SnagSum, and
SnagOut.)  Modified dbs.kwd and keylist.prm.

esm 12/13/04
Added the new ThinMist keyword. Modified the basekeys.kwd and keylist.prm files.

sar 12/08/04
Added the new FFE event monitor functions and fixed the POTFLEN function
in function.evm.

dav 12/07/04
Updated "Grep" command line associated with producing !run!.err error log
file.

sar 11/23/04
Added the SalvSP keyword in fire.kwd and keylist.prm.

cek 10/28/04
Made changes to species names for Swamp tupelo and blackgum in CS
species list in species.prm.

cek 10/28/04
Made changes to the BAMAX keyword in basekeys.prm. Changed CR models
to allow users to enter a BAMAX, not AMD percent.

sar 08/18/04
Made changes to the BAMAX and SDIMAX keywords in basekeys.prm.  Changed
BAMAX so that it could be selected with any variant and changed SDIMAX
so that it could be selected with the CS, LS, and NE variants.

cek 07/12/04
Added dbs to all x-executables and cs executable in programsWindosOnly.prm.

dav 06/30/04
Create an Error log file from the Main Output file. The Error log file
reports FVS error messages that are displayed with the Main Output file.
Added ability to view Error log file within Suppose -- Select Post
Processor window.

nlc/sar 05/21/04
Added options for POTFLEN function for Total and Surface fire flame lengths.

esm 05/20/04
Added a new keyword, DEFECT. The only files modified were basekeys.kwd
and keylist.prm. Also made a correction to the 2 digit alpha code for
Cottonwood in the CS varaint, it was CW, it has been changed to EC. Only
the species.prm file was modified for this correction.

esm 04/28/04
Made a correction to the CWEQN keyword. Only file modified in correction
was the basekeys.kwd file.

esm 03/19/04
Added two new keywords FIXCW and CWEQN. Modified the default value of
field 5 on the FIXDG, FIXCW, FIXMORT and FIXHTG keywords from 0.0 to 999.0

esm 03/19/04
added fire to the wcx in the program.prm and programsWindosOnly.prm file.

esm 02/20/04
modified basekeys.kwd, changed the description on fields 6 and 7 of
HTGSTOP so that they would be correct and match the Keyword Guide.

nlc 01/28/04
added dbs keywords MisRpts and CutList. Corrected TreesOut to TreeList.

sar 01/12/04
modified fire.kwd and keylist.prm to create the new CanCalc keyword.

sar 01/06/04
modified fire.kwd to change the Defulmod keyword.  Designated that the
loadings should be entered in lbs/ft2.

sar 01/06/04
modified basekeys.kwd to change the Yardloss keyword.  Modified it to
take into account the different interpretation for the SN variant.  Also
tried to make the parameter labels easier to understand.

sar 01/06/04
modified fire.kwd to change the moisture categories on the simfire
keyword.  originally, the categories were Very Dry, Dry, Wet, and Very
Wet.  They were corrected to match the FFE documentation (Very Dry, Dry,
Moist, Wet).  Also, other labels were used in the SN variant, per their
request (Extremely Dry, Very Dry, Dry, Wet).

esm 12/10/03
modified program.prm and programWindosOnly.prm. the crx varaint was not
recognizing the annosus extension because the 3 had been left off of the
'ardwrd', the 3 has been now been added.

dav 12/08/03
modified uneven-aged group select to handle broader input parameter
specifications.

esm 11/13/03
in species.prm changed the 2 letter species alpha code for oregon ash in
the CA variant from OA to FL to match the FVS code.

esm 10/24/03
added additional description on the sitecode keyword regarding Dunning
codes, and simplified the description of site in the IE variant.

nlc 10/23/03
added scorch height to FlameAdj keyword

sar 10/22/03
modified program.prm and programWindosOnly.prm so that cafm, wcfm, and
pnfm are recognized.  Also added fire to the designations of iex, pnx,
and ncx.

esm 10/23/03
modified mist.kwd, the mistletoe keywords were not working coorectly for
the kt and ie varaints.

sar 10/16/03
modified ppif.prm to recognize the fire and fuels table post processors
in the aix version.

sar 10/08/03
modified program.prm and programWindosOnly.prm to recognize iex.

sar 09/10/03
changed a description on the simfire keyword so that it doesn't ask
for wind speed 20 feet above the ground, which is incorrect.

mgv & nlc 06/25/03
Added a post processor to create a combined FFE report.

esm 08/21/03
Modified the STINFO keyword to default to blanks in basekeys.kwd.
Also modified forest.prm and all hab_.prms to accept a blank as
a valid field.

dav 08/08/03
Modified diameter class breaks within unevage.prm to properly handle
beginning diameter class.

sar 08/08/03
Modified program.prm and programsWindosOnly.prm to recognize iefm.

esm 07/29/03
Modified basekeys.prm. Changed the 5 to a 15 in the caution of
the TreeData keyword.

nlc 07/25/03
Added dbs extension to programs: ls, ppls, ne, pppn (Windows only).
Added switches to DBS Compute keyword.

esm 07/25/03
Added IE variant. Modified species.prm, programWindowsOnly.prm,
program.prm, forest.prm, variant.prm, mist.kwd, basekeys.kwd,
mkprm.bat, and added habpa_ie.prm.

sar 07/15/03
Modified program.prm and programsWindosOnly.prm to recognize
ncfm and snfm.

nlc 06/25/03
Modified the the DSNIn and DSNOut keyword support for the DBS
extension.

mgv 06/25/03
Changed the calls to several of the post processors to reflect
the new executable names, and removed the call to the editor
for PC post processors.  Changed the default for the third field
of YardLoss from 0 to 1.

nlc 06/18/03
added support for the system command (base and ppe).

sr & nlc 06/17/03
modified the sprout keyword to support recent change.

nlc 06/02/03
modified the database keywords and added database support
to all programs (Windows Only). Added the definition of the
Fire and Fuels Extension plus PPE for ni and bm variants.

dav 05/21/03
corrected the batch command for executing the RMVSS post
processor.  Second replaceable parameter needed to cite the
*.key file instead of *.out file.

dav 05/19/03
corrected text scripts associated with the cfvolequ and bfvoleq
keywords.  Clarified the descriptions.

dav 04/25/03
developed an uneven-aged management action for Group Selection
silviculture.  Compiled previous efforts by Winkler, Donnelly,
and Tech.  Added Vandendriesche enhancements.  Good approximation
within the confines of a semi-distance independent model.

dav 04/21/03
reworked DOS batch command for removing empty SVS folder.  Needed
for Windows 2000+ operating systems.

nlc 04/09/03
add first cut of data base keywords and added program definitions
that include that extension.

dav 03/10/03
modified uneven-aged management actions to account for a diameter
class increment that is not in sync with the diameter range that is
specified. Adjusted Legacy Tree thinning parameters.

dav 02/20/03
modified uneven-aged management actions to allow thinning above
maximum range diameter to maintain basal area or sdi stand
target.

sar 02/18/03
Fixed spelling error in description of MortClas in keylist.prm

sar 01/28/03
Changed descriptions of PotFWind, FlameAdj, and SimFire keywords in
fire.kwd.

mgv 01/10/03
Corrected field 2 of the MistPref keyword to refer to AK instead
of SE in the list of f2v values.

nlc 01/08/03
Fixed the ShrubPC and ShrubHt keywords for the Cover Extension.

mgv 12/30/02
Added Event Monitor variables: BMaxHS, AMaxHS, BMinHS, AMinHS,
BNumSS, and ANumSS. Changed the description for the PASSALL
keyword in keylist.prm and estab.kwd.  Added the parameter
field for PASSALL in estab.kwd.

nlc 11/07/02
removed the UTM codes from the LOCATE keyword.

sar 11/04/02
added the "always" case to the fire variables in variable.evm, so that
the fire variables always appear in the variables list in the free
form editor.

nlc 11/01/02
Added new Event Monitor variables: ForTyp, SizCls, and StkCls.

Modified the Locate keyword support to include the state and county
codes (the UTM data was already supported).

Changed the old name "Fuels and Fire Effects Model" to the standard
name "Fire and Fuels Extension". This change was done is several
places to insure consistent use of terms.

Lance David 9/12/02
Added the 'x' executables and removed the individual i/p executables
from the program.prm file. FFE is included in the x where available.

sar 08/29/02
Changed description of FuelTret keyword (so no stand entry/harvest
is implied).

sar 08/22/02
Added default values to description of PileBurn keyword.
Corrected error with PotFMois keyword (moderate fire = 2, not 0).
Set categories of FuelPool to match FFE user's guide (very slow,
slow, fast, very fast).

mgv 08/21/02
Fixed the values for the fifth parameter of the SVS keyword in
basekeys.kwd.  Changed default for field 2 of GROWTH for SN to 5.
Removed unsupported values for field 1 of OUTPUT in estab.kwd,
and changed default for field 2 to 17.

nlc 07/23/02
Changed program definition for ecfm so that strp is used rather than estb.
Changed the ppe CopySum keyword so that it does not include an open
statement.

mgv, nlc, lance 07/22/02
Fixed the mistletoe model MistPref keyword species lists and the Fire
model default duff production for the DuffProd keyword.

mgv and nlc 06/26/02
Add support for ThinCC and modified the support
for the SpMcDBH function.

nlc 06/17/02
Modified SVS keyword to support creation of ground files.  Refined the
FFE Salvage, PileBurn, and SnagFall keyword prompt strings.

mgv 06/12/02
Added new values 10, 11, 20, and 21 to field 7 of FIXMORT.

mgv 06/10/02
Added a reference to the effects in the eastern US to the descriptions
in basekeys.kwd for BFDEFECT, BFFDLN, MCDEFECT, and MCFDLN.

nlc 06/03/02
Modified the parms entries for for the FFE keywords: FuelRept,
MortRept, and Moisture. Added NoCopSum and CopySum ppe keywords.

mgv 05/06/02
Added the new fifth field to the MINHARV keyword in basekeys.kwd.

nlc 05/02/02
Made several changes to the FFE-related entries to make it conform to the
new user's guide.  These changes are outlined in the FFE-FVS release
notes issued in May 2002.

mgv 04/17/02
Added support for SN to MANAGED keyword in basekeys.kwd

nlc 04/03/02
Added, to program.prm, definitions for bmfm, crfm, and ttfm (fire
model).

mgv 04/03/02
Added list of forest types for third field of the MODTYPE keyword for SN in
basekeys.kwd.  Also removed the obsolete sixth field of the MORTMULT keyword
and fixed the parms format for FIXDG and FIXHTG.  In ppif.prm the calls to
the editor were removed for several post processors that have been rewritten
so that they no longer need that call.

mgv 02/20/02
Added definition of CIFM and ECFM to program list.

mgv 10/01/01
Added the Locate, NoScreen, and TFixArea keywords to basekeys.kwd and keylist.prm.

nlc 06/06/01
Added definition of Western Sierra Fire Model to program list.

mgv 06/05/01
Added the SerlCorr keyword to basekeys.kwd and keylist.prm.
Changed the default model type for CR on ModType to 2.

ajm 05/29/01
Modified wwpb.kwd to reflect coding changes.  Users no longer enter filenames or unit
numbers when requesting WWPB model output files.  Changes made for WWPB model keywords:
BMTOTALS, BMDETAIL, and BMDVOUT.

jhk  04/30/01
Edited mist.kwd (keyword Mistmort) so that the word mortiplier now reads multiplier.
I also edited armward3.kwd (keywords InocSpan, PlotInf, PlRead, RRJump, RRMink,
Spread, and TTDMult) so that all keywords were set up for Armillaria Root Disease and
not Annosus Root Disease.  Finally I edited phewrd3.kwd (keywords PlotInf, RRJump,
and RRMink) so that all keywords were set up for Laminated Root Rot and
not Armillaria Root Disease

mgv 04/12/01
Added SDI as eleventh value for return from SPMCDBH function.
Removed incorrect reference to post processors in the description for
the CutList keyword.  Changed wording for the selection of cycle 1
output for the TreeList and FvsStand keywords.  Added support for a
spruce beetle risk rating post processor.

nlc 01/19/01
Fire Model changes: Modified text and input order for Moisture
keyword, deleted PotFire, added PotFMois and PotFWind keywords.

nlc 01/03/01
Added the Drought keyword to the Fire Model.  Added program
definitions for the UT and CR Fire Model.

nlc 12/28/00
Modified the Open keyword to take advantage of the new "fileBrowse"
feature.

nlc 12/27/00
Added the FuelMove keyword to the FFE (change to keylist.prm), and
edited FireType and FuelBurn keywords in fire.kwd. Also fixed a
problem with field 2 of SDIMax and changed the prompt string for the
SiteCode keyword (in basekeys.kwd).

ajm 12/6/00
Extensive changes made to wsbwe.kwd and wsbwd.kwd.
Made related changes in program.prm, exten.prm and keylist.prm

changes to wsbwe.kwd:
-Fixed column widths in answerform for GENDEFOL. Ammended description.
-Corrected text describing output file names in BWOUTPUT.
-Ammended descriptive text clarifying the use of each keyword.
-Added DAMAGE and PERDAM as keyword choices to the General Defoliation
Model.

changes to wsbwd.kwd:
-Added keyword SETPRBIO
-Consolidated the Pkeys that heretofore were separated by model type
(within the CR variant) into one Pkey for CR. (for keyword DEFOL).
-Corrected tree species codes for all variants.  Added WL as a
host-choice to all
(applicable) variants (keywords DEFOL, SETPRBIO).
-Removed NoTopKl
-Ammended descriptive text throughout.

Changes to program.prm
-Associated "wsbwd" to/with all *e executables.  The *d executables
are now obsolete.
-The "wsbwd" keywords are now a "subset" of the General Defoliation
Model keywords, and become available to a Suppose user via a different
"extension" (The 'General Defoliation Model: "manual" defoliation').
Whenever the General Defoliation Model is available (a model with the
"e" suffix on the executable name), two "extensions" will be
available: the one mentioned above (the old damage model), and the
'General Defoliation Model(replaces the WSBW Model)' extension (the
old defoliation model).

Changes made to exten.prm
Changed the names of the extensions: The 'Western Spruce Budworm
Damage Model' is now the 'General Defoliation Model "Manual"
Defoliation' extension.  The 'General(W.S.B) Defoliation' extension is
now the 'General Defoliation Model (replaces the WSBW model)'
extension.

Changes made to keylist.prm
-Added SETPRBIO to wsbwd
-Removed NOTOPKL
-Ammended descriptions throughout the General Defoliation Model section
-Made DAMAGE and PERDAM belong to both wsbwd and wsbwe.


awc 11/1/00
Modified the parameters for armwrd3 keyword "STRead".
Corrected the fourth argument, default (3) to correctly identify
Armillaria root disease instead of P-Type Annosus (1).

mgv 10/19/00
Added the ThinSDI keyword.  Added SDI as the eleventh value
for the first argument of the SpMcDBH function.  Made 9.6
the default for BFVolume DIB in CS, LS, and NE.  Made several
small modifications to the basekeys.kwd file to make the
keyword descriptions more consistent and remove odd characters
that printed in the keyword descriptions in Suppose.

nlc 9/11/00
Added plot boundary support to SVS keyword.

nlc 3/27/00
Added ktfm to the list of programs, modified the SVS keyword to
support drawing range poles.

nlc 8/23/00
Removed CntlZ from wsbwe.kwd, added SVIMAGES keyword for the fire
extension.

mgv 8/3/00
Added blue spruce, pinyon pine, western juniper, and gambel oak to
the species list for UT, bringing the total to 14 species.
Changed species listed as western white pine in all Central Rockies
variants to southwestern white pine.

dav 8/2/00
Added three additional Uneven-Aged Management Actions.  The original
indiv. tree. selection (ITS) BA uses ThinDBH which ignores SpecPref
inclusion.  A new ITS-BA which uses ThinBBA was developed to enable
species discrimation.  Two new ITS Stand Density Index Management
Actions were also developed; one with ThinDBH; one with ThinBBA.

mgv 5/26/00
Added support for the new seventh field of the FixMort keyword.
Added support for habitat type as the second field of the StdInfo
keyword in all Central Rockies variants.  Made one correction to
the habpa_ni.prm file.

mgv 5/17/00
Added support for the FixDG and FixHtG keywords.  Fixed the parmsForm
for several keywords which were writing the date/cycle to column 21.
Added support for a tenth value (average diameter growth) of the first
argument of the SpMcDBH function.  Made 50=oak-hickory the default
forest type for the ModType keyword in the Southeast variant.

ajm 4/18/00
Changed WWPB model/ppe Debug and NoDebug entries back to (No)Debug_Top,
(No)Debug_Bottom, and (No)Debug_report.

ajm April 14, 2000
Fixed 2 WWPB model entries in Keylist.prm (Reprodn and BMTotals).
Fixed line 9 in Ppekeys.kwd (brackets missing)

ajm April 13, 2000
Ammended ppekeys.kwd.  Fixed the answerForm and parmsForm for AreaLocs,
Neighbor, and Rdaccess so that the associated OPEN and CLOSE statements
are appropriately placed.

ajm Apr 11, 2000
Added one WWPB model keyword to list in Keylist.prm (Aphero)
Made extensive changes to WWPB model defaults in WWPB.kwd.  Also added
more explanatory text to various keywords.
Enabled PPCRP and PPNIP in Program.prm (they were heretofore commented
out.)
Created PPSOP and PPCIP in Program.prm

nlc Apr 7, 2000
Fixed program entry for ppni, added ppnir.

mgv Mar 25, 2000
Added support for cr (in addition to the existing sw, sp, lp,
bp, and sf) to the mist.kwd file.

bal March 15, 2000
Added support for the Southern Variant (SN).

nlc, from Dave Graham March 15, 2000
Support for the GenDefol (a.k.a Budlite) was added as follows:
program.prm - new *e programs
exten.prm - new wsbwe extension
keylist.prm - new wsbwe keys
wsbwe.kwd - the new keywords

The mkprm.bat file was also updated to add wsbwe.kwd...unix
version is ok as is.

nlc Feb 17, 2000
Added several PPE entries to the programs (from Gary).

nlc Feb 10, 2000
Added sofm to the programs.

nlc Jan 31, 2000
Changed answerform to answerForm in ppekeys, global change.

nlc Jan 30, 2000
Added some PPE programs and fixed the MsPolicy keyword.

dav Jan 18, 2000
Tweaked the cutting logic for the Uneven-aged BA Management Action
routine.

nlc Dec 14, 1999
Fixed the ReadCor* keywords for the cr variants...the answerForm
statements all had ReadCorD, even for ReadCorH & R. Add a range check
to the DgStdDev keyword.

nlc Dec 9, 1999
Added cr to the list of variants with srouting species.

nlc Dec 7, 1999
Added "parms" support for several Fire model keywords.

nlc Dec 6, 1999
Added first draft of the West Wide Bark Beetle and PPE keywords
as they were sent by Dave Graham. However, the programs that
contain the PPE were commented out. The AddFile change listed below
had somehow been lost and was restored. Put in the change for the
CR variant that Don Vandendriesche posted for ReadCor*.

nlc Oct 15,1999
Modified the uneven aged mgmt keywords as requested by Don V.

nlc Oct 1, 1999
Added the "Indiv tree select, basal area target" mgmt action of Don
Vandendriesche to the parms file.  This inlcuded adding a file to
the parms file set called unevageba.prm and modifying
mgmtcats.prm. Also modified support for the FVSStand keyword.  Updated
mkprm.bat to reflect the addition of unevageba.prm

mgv Sep 15, 1999
Fixed parms form for RegDMult and RegHMult in basekeys.kwd to
have the correct number of parameters.  Changed several species
alpha codes in species.prm: bitter cherry to CH, black cottonwood
to CW, shasta red fir to SH, Brewer spruce to BR, blue oak to BL,
walnut to WN, California laurel to CL, hawthorn to HT, blue ash
to UA.  Ordered species lists alphabetically by variant code,
however ni is still listed first due to the descriptions included.
Removed Cover from program.prm extension list in ak, ca, and cr.

mgv Aug 24, 1999
Removed support for the post processor to view the EchoSum file.
Added the second supplemental record for the BFVolEqu and CFVolEqu
keywords, and corrected the order of the second and third fields
of these keywords.  Modified descriptions for fields 1 and 3 of
the Growth keyword.  Changed the SDIMax keyword for the new format
where fields 3 and 4 are no longer supported, and fields 5 and 6
set the SDI thresholds.

nlc Aug 19, 1999
Removed support for the older version of SVS.  Edited the description
of the SVS post processors to refer to "SVS tree list files" and
deleteing the use of the term "SVS image" files.

mgv Aug 18, 1999
Added support for options 8 and 9 of field 1 of SPMCDBH function.
Added selection options for volume calculation method for the
BFVOLUME and VOLUME keywords in cs, ls, ne, se.  Options were
updated for the SDIMAX keyword to be consistent with FVS.

mgv (noted by nlc) Jun 10, 1999
Fixed spelling of pondersosa pine.  Changed the Central Rockies
submodels to all have the 24-species list which we are now using, and
change BS in the Lake States variant to be black spruce instead of
blue spruce.  Nuttall oak was NO and Osage orange was OR.  These have
been changed to NK and OO respectively. Added _se to //end species.
Fixed several spelling mistakes.

nlc May 20, 1999
General edit of the fire model keywords...added support of MortClas.

nlc May 7, 1999
Modified the plant association list for the BM variant.

nlc May 6, 1999
Added support for new SVS keyword (basekeys and keylist), modified the
run commands to create a subdirectory for the SVS files, added 2 new
post processors for the WINSVS command used with the new SVS
keyword. Modified the Debug keyword, modified the cr variant entry for
SDIMAX, modifed a few fire model keywords. Implimented "Use Parms" in
the following Estab keyword: ResetAge, HtAdj, SpecMult, StockAdj

mgv May 5, 1999
Added support for the BAMax and SDIMax keywords in the se variant.
Modified these keywords for new cr features including a new field 7 in
SDIMax.  Updated the forest.prm file to include the current list of
district codes (which are needed in addition to the region and forest
code for the se variant).  Made minor changes to wording of some
keyword field descriptions.

mgv Jan 11, 1999
Added support for a variant labeled 'cr' which recognizes 24
species codes and which should eventually replace the submodel
labels sw, sp, sf, lp, and bp.
Made the obsolete Model Type field in the StdInfo keyword
inactive for the Central Rockies models.
Included support for the Prune and FVSStand keywords and the
FVSStand and TOSS post processors.

nlc Oct 28, 1998
Added enties for ReadCor[D,H,R] for the ca variant.  Modified the
"movies" option to build a directory that does not have the .svs
suffix in the name.

nlc Oct 26, 1998
Modified fields for SpMcDBH function and added field 7 of StrClass.

mgv Oct 14, 1998
Standardized alpha species codes for LS (Lake States), CS (Central
States), NE (Northeast), SE (Southeast) variants.  Made a few more
changes to ppif.prm

mgv Sept 23, 1998
Modified the basekeys.kwd, forest.prm, species.prm, and variants.prm
to add support for the ca variant.
Added HabPa_ca.
Made some changes to the descriptions in ppif.prm.

nlc Sept 18, 1998
Fixed the Open keyword (formated/unformated option was wrong)
Added the Close keyword to keylist and basekeys
Changed the order of the nifm and nifr programs.

nlc July 20, 1998
Fixed AddFile (see rn109.txt).

mjo June 25, 1998
Retired the old root disease entries, fixed a few bugs, and
 updated the naming conventions for Western Root Disease.
 1)Removed annosus.kwd, armillar.kwd and phellinu.kwd. Updated the
   mkprm.bat to reflect these changes.
 2)Modified program.prm to:
   a) Remove *r3 lines (old Western Root Disease v. 3.0).
   b) Remove *a lines (old annosus root disease).
   c) Add ardwrd3 to the *r lines (new Western Root Disease).
   d) Add ardwrd3 to the multi-pest programs (*x) if present.
   e) Add ncr and wsr to the list.
 3)Modified keylist.prm and exten.prm to remove old root disease blocks
   and update new WRD entries.
 4)Modified armwrd3.kwd to disable 'annosus root disease type' option
   in RRInit.
 5)Modified ardwrd3.kwd to make repairs in RRType. RRType won't work
   properly with Suppose v.1.08, and these repairs are only valid
   with v.1.07 for now.

nlc May 15, 1998.
Made changes as listed in rn108.txt

nlc April 17, 1998.
Modified the AK variant species list.

nlc April 15, 1998.
Added the entries for wrd3, as follows:
 Added ardwrd3, armwrd3, and phewrd3 to exten.prm
 Modified program.prm to add programs that include these extensions
 Modified mgmtcats.prm to include the borax and pushing of stumps
 Modified keylist.prm by adding references to the keywords for these
   extensions and moved the anossus entries to be grouped with the
   other disease keywords
 Added ardwrd3.kwd, armwrd3.kwd, phewrd3.kwd as prepared by Matt
   Oberle to the MKPRM.BAT macro.
 Notice: I did not remove the old root disease entries.

nlc April 9, 1998.
Structral classification modifications were made to support the new
logic and keywords.

rmt/nlc Feb 20 1998.
Teck made some changes in the ppif.prm

nlc Feb 17 1998.
Modified new regen window entries to correctly deal with the cr
variants.

nlc Feb 2 1998.
Added entries to support the new regeneration window.

nlc/rmt, Jan 7, 1998.
Added winsvs, sumavg, and calibrat to ppif.prm.

nlc, Nov. 6, 1997.

Added access to canopy cover in the spmcdbh function and added the
SStage event monitor variables to the lists.

nlc, Sept 3&4, 1997.

Added the ModType keyword, fixed the fire model keywords, fixed SStage
keyword.

nlc, Aug 20, 1997.

Modified commands.prm to finaly fix drag and drop on .key files.

nlc, April 3, 1997.

Added HabPa_wc and _pn from Renate.

nlc, March 10, 1997.

Replaced keyword_categories and keyword_list as Renate sent them.
Added the YardLoss keyword.

nlc, Feb 25, 1997 ... and Feb 27.

Added new keylist, basekeys, and cover, and estab...from Renate.

nlc, Feb 18, 1997

Replaced keylist and basekeys with that from Renate.  Fixed spelling
of ThinHt.  Added support for SpCodes, StdIdent, and MgmtID.  Note
that the last 2 do not cause changes in Suppose's name for these stands.

nlc, Feb 12, 1997

Replaced as modifed by Renate variants, species, forests, and HabPa_so.

nlc, Jan 8, 1997

Added fire model keywords to keylist.prm and created fire.kwd

nlc, Jan 7, 1997

Edited the ppif.prm file to add/modify (or NOT added, see below) entries
as listed below:

compute
  Updated the command line and edited the description.

sumavgsp
  Not added because it reads the .rsm file Suppose does not create
that file.

avcompsp
  Added entry ... but it may not work because I think it uses the .rms
file.

freq
  Updated entry.

standtab, btlrisk, calowl, rmvss, boisevss
  Added entries.

compute2
  Did NOT add entry... it seems too redundant to compute given that in
Suppose, a user can not specify a list of desired variables.

===========================================================================

Matt Thompson, Dec 30, 1996:

keylist.prm    - added: lodgepole mountain pine beetle
                        douglas-fir beetle
                        western spruce budworm damage
                        annosus root disease

               - modified Armillaria and Phellinus (Laminated Root Rot)
                 sections

exten.prm      - Modified Mountain Pine Beetle and Phellinus
                 PStrings

program.prm    - Added all variants and current pest model associations.

keycats.prm    - Added the category "outbreak"

variants.prm   - Added the pn variant

phellinus.prm  - Changed name to phellinu.kwd  (8 character name for PC)

               - Modified a couple things to make it consistent with
                 Armillaria

armillaria.prm - Changed name to armillar.kwd  (8 character name for PC)

               - Modified a couple things to make it consistent with
                 Phellinus

lpmpb.kwd      - new

dfb.kwd        - new

wsbwd.kwd      - new

annosus.kwd    - new



